# Kai Li

Office 1195, 3675 Market St., Philadelphia, PA, 19104

#### kl696@drexel.edu

#### http://kaili.us

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

Kai Li is interested in scholarly communication, open science, and scientometrics, especially (1) how digital research objects, such as software and datasets, and research activities are represented in scientific publications through scientific writing practices and (2) how the existing scientific infrastructure can be improved to facilitate a better integration of scientific research and writing practices.

## **EDUCATION**

2015- PhD, Information Studies; College of Computing and Informatics, Drexel

University, Philadelphia PA (ABD; expected to graduate in June, 2020)

2012-2013 Master of Science, Library and Information Science; School of Information Studies,

Syracuse University, Syracuse NY

2003-2007 BA, History; School of History, Beijing Normal University, Beijing, China

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2015- Graduate Research Assistant; Drexel University 2012-2014 Research Assistant; Syracuse University

## **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Refereed Journal Papers**

- Yan, E., Chen, Z., & Li, K. (In press). Authors' status and the perceived quality of their work: measuring citation sentiment change in Nobel papers. *Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology*.
- Li, K., Greenberg, J., & Dunic, J. (In press). Data objects and documenting scientific processes: An analysis of data events in biodiversity data papers. *Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology*.
- Li, K., Chen, P.-Y., & Yan, E. (2019). Challenges of measuring software impact through citations: An examination of the Ime4 R package. *Journal of Informetrics*, 13(1), 449–461. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2019.02.007">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2019.02.007</a>
- Li, K., & Yan, E. (2019). Are NIH-funded publications fulfilling the proposed research? An
  examination of concept-matchedness between NIH research grants and their supported
  publications. *Journal of Informetrics*, 13(1), 226–237. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2019.01.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2019.01.001</a>
- Li, Y., Wu, C., Yan, E., & Li, K. (2018). Will open access increase journal CiteScores? An empirical investigation over multiple disciplines. *PLOS ONE*, 13(8), e0201885. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0201885">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0201885</a>
- Yan, E., & Li, K. (2018). Which domains do open-access journals do best in? A 5-year longitudinal study. *Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology*, 69(6), 844–856. https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.24002
- Li, K., Rollins, J., & Yan, E. (2018). Web of Science use in published research and review papers 1997–2017: a selective, dynamic, cross-domain, content-based analysis.

- Scientometrics, 115(1), 1-20. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-017-2622-5
- Zhao, M., Yan, E., & Li, K. (2018). Data set mentions and citations: A content analysis of full-text publications. *Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology*, 69(1), 32–46. https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.23919
- Li, K. & Yan, E. (2018). Co-mention network of R packages: Scientific impact and clustering structure. *Journal of Informetrics*, 12(1), 87-100. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2017.12.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2017.12.001</a>
- Li, K., Yan, E., & Feng, Y. (2017). How is R cited in research outputs? Structure, impacts, and citation standard. *Journal of Informetrics*, 11(4), 989–1002. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2017.08.003

#### **Refereed Full Papers in Conference Proceedings**

- Li, K., & Yan, E. (2019). Using a keyword extraction pipeline to understand concepts in future work sections of research papers. In 17th International Conference on Scientometrics and Informetrics.
- Feng, Y., Li, K., & Agosto, D.E. (2017). Healthy users' personal health information management from activity trackers: The perspective of gym-goers. In *Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of Association for Information Science & Technology* (54: pp. 71-81). doi:10.1002/pra2.2017.14505401009
- Li, K., Greenberg, J., & Lin, X. (2016). Software Citation, Reuse and Metadata Considerations: An Exploratory Study Examining LAMMPS. In *Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Information Science and Technology* (53: pp. 1-10). doi:10.1002/pra2.2016.14505301072
- Qin, J., & Li, K. (2013). How portable are the metadata standards for scientific data? a proposal for a metadata infrastructure. In *Proceedings of the International Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications* (pp. 25–34). <u>Link</u>

#### **Refereed Short Papers in Conference Proceedings**

- Pascua, S., Li, K., & Greenberg, J. (2019). Toward A Metadata Activity Matrix: Conceptualizing and Grounding the Research Life-cycle and Metadata Connections. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications.
- Guerra, J., Wei, Q., Kai, L., Ahumada, L., Winston, F., & Desai, B. R. (2018). Scosy: A
  Biomedical Collaboration Recommendation System. Presented at the 40th Annual
  International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC),
  Honolulu, HI, USA.

#### **Refereed Conference Posters**

- Li, K., Chen, P.-Y., Fang, Z. (2019). Disciplinarity of Software Papers: A Preliminary Analysis. In *Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of Association for Information Science & Technology* (56).
- Li, K., & Chen, P.-Y. (2019). A preliminary scientometric analysis of the Cross-Strait scientific collaboration. In 17th International Conference on Scientometrics and Informetrics.
- He, J. & Li, K. (2019). How comprehensive is the PubMed Central Open Access full-text database? Presented at iConferece 2019 Annual Meeting, Washington, DC, USA.
- Li, K. & Chen, PY. (2018). The narrative structure as a citation context in data papers: A preliminary analysis of *Scientific Data*. In *Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of Association for Information Science & Technology* (55).
- Li, K. & Xu, S. (2017). Measuring the impact of R packages. InProceedings of the Annual Meeting of Association for Information Science & Technology (54: pp. 739-741). doi:10.1002/pra2.2017.14505401138
- Li, K. (2017). A metadata scheme of the software-data relationship: A proposal. Presented in Research Data Alliance 9th Plenary Meeting, Barcelona, Spain, April 5-8, 2017.
- Li, K., Ahumada, L., & Desai, B. (2017). SchoRSys: a scholar recommendation system based on content-based filtering technique and PubMed metadata records. Presented in Drexel University 9th Annual Research Symposium, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, March 3, 2017.
- Li, K. (2016). How much can data citation standards be used for scientific software? A crosswalk analysis of data citation standards for software citation needs. Presented in Research Data Alliance 8th Plenary Meeting, Denver, Colorado, September 14-17, 2016.

#### **Book Reviews**

Li, K. (2019). A review of The Politics of Mass Digitization. Education for Information, 35, 361-363. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3233/EFI-199011">https://doi.org/10.3233/EFI-199011</a>

#### **Non-Refereed Conference Presentations**

• Li, K. (2012, June 24). RDA in China. ALA Annual Conference 2012, Anaheim, California. Link

## **TEACHING**

#### Instructor:

Information Visualization (INFO250), Summer, 2019, Drexel University

#### **Teaching Assistant:**

- Introduction to Data Analytics (INFO659), Fall, 2019, Drexel University
- Information Visualization (INFO250), Winter 2018, Drexel University
- Resources for Children (INFO683), Summer 2018, Drexel University
- Introduction to Computing and Informatics (CI101), Fall 2015, Drexel University

### **GRANTS AND FELLOWSHIPS**

2019	International Conference on Scientometrics & Informetrics Student Travel Award, The International Society for Informetrics and Scientometrics (Awarded \$1,500 for travel support)
2019	LIS Education and Data Science for the National Digital Platform (LEADS-4-NDP)
	Fellowship; Drexel University (Awarded \$5,000 plus travel support)
2016-2017	RDA/US Data Share Fellowship; Research Data Alliance (Awarded \$10,000 plus
	travel support)

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2016-2017 Research Internship; The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia

- Developed scholar recommendation system based on MeSH subject terms, text-mining techniques, and social network
- Designed and implement a Natural Language Processing system to analyze full-text clinician notes

2014-2015 Cataloger; Ingram Content Group

- Performed original and copy cataloging, subject analysis, and shelflist based on national and local cataloging standards
- Proofread cataloging records made by other catalogers, and trained new catalogers

2007-2012 Cataloging Librarian; Capital Library of China, Beijing, China

 Performed original and copy cataloging and subject analysis using national and local standards

## **EDITORIAL SERVICE**

#### Reviewer:

- Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology
- Journal of Informetrics
- Scientometrics
- · Library Hi Tech

- iConference (2019)
- AMIA Annual Symposium (2017-)

## **MEMBERSHIPS**

## **Professional Associations:**

• Association for Information Science and Technology (ASIS&T)